"Like Beet Juice, Taurine Supplementation
May Only Be Safe in the Context of a Plant-Based Diet"
In my last videos,
I mentioned how the best choice
might be to eat
a healthy plant-based diet
with supplemental taurine,
but it’s possible
that taking taurine,
whether from bulk powder,
supplements, energy drinks,
or even shellfish,
may only be safe in the context
of a healthy plant-based diet.
In the remarkable study that
launched this video series,
taurine supplementation
of lab animals
increased their lifespan
and/or healthspan.
However, the impact of taurine
dietary supplementation
on the gut microbiome
was not addressed.
Oral administration of taurine
results in an increase
of taurine-conjugated
bile acids,
for example,
quadrupling the percentage
of taurocholic acid.
That’s not good,
because higher levels
of taurocholic acid in humans
is associated
with a shorter lifespan.
For each
standard deviation increase
in a measure
of taurocholate,
which is just buffered
taurocholic acid,
the odds of achieving
longevity in humans
appeared to decrease
by almost 40 percent,
a 30 percent lower chance
of making it to age 80.
What happens is the metabolism
of these
taurine-conjugated bile acids
by our gut microbes
generates the rotten egg gas,
hydrogen sulfide,
which doesn’t
just give you smelly farts,
but is a DNA-damaging compound.
So, hydrogen sulfide could be
a significant
bacterial metabolite
that initiates colon cancer.
And that’s just the half of it.
Taurocholic acid gets split
into taurine and cholic acid.
The taurine goes on
to produce hydrogen sulfide,
which is pro-inflammatory
and could trigger DNA mutations,
and the cholic acid
gets turned into a toxic,
so-called secondary bile acid,
called deoxycholic acid,
known as DCA, which also
produces inflammation
and can promote growing tumors.
So, gut microbes can
metabolize the taurocholic acid
into hydrogen sulfide and DCA,
which are genotoxins
and tumor promoters,
respectively,
and could intensify
aging symptoms in the host.
Therefore, consumption
of a diet low in taurine
may contribute to the reduced
frequency of cancer.
Taurine can promote the growth
of a taurine-metabolizing
bacteria,
Bilophila wadsworthia,
which thrive on taurine.
Those bacteria take the taurine
and turn it
into hydrogen sulfide,
which is linked to a weaker
colonic mucus barrier,
inflammatory bowel disease,
and colorectal cancer.
So, it’s not just cancer.
The increased taurocholate
caused by
taurine supplementation
is associated with
a reduced lifespan in humans
in the absence
of any relation to risk
for cardiovascular disease
or for cancer.
But the effects
of hydrogen sulfide
can be stopped.
The cells that line our colon
express protective enzymes
that can detoxify
hydrogen sulfide.
How can we boost those enzymes?
Butyrate boosts those
detoxification enzymes,
protecting our cells
from the sulfide gas.
Remember butyrate?
That’s what our good
gut bugs make from fiber.
So, there’s this struggle
between the sulfide
made by the bad bugs in the gut
versus the butyrate made
by the good bugs in our gut.
Hydrogen sulfide can cause
hyperproliferation,
a signal of potential
colon cancer development,
but it can be reversed
if you drip on some butyrate,
like you would get naturally
by just eating
a high-fiber diet.
That’s just half
of the protection, though.
The sulfur-containing
amino acids, like taurine,
and diets high in animal protein
aren’t the only factors
that select for the bad bacteria
that create the toxic,
tumor-promoting,
secondary bile acids,
there’s also the animal fat.
When people were given taurine,
like the half a gram
three times a day
I suggested in my last video,
there was a marked increase
in the proportion of
taurine-conjugated bile acids,
but what we care about
is how many are actually
excreted into our gut.
This is how it’s envisioned.
On an animal-based diet,
not only is there more taurine,
leading to a higher ratio of
taurine-conjugated bile acids,
but also more bile secretion
owing to
the higher fat consumption.
High-fat diets are associated
with increased taurine
conjugation in humans,
but not just any fat,
specifically saturated fat.
Consumption of a diet
high in saturated fat,
in this case butter fat,
but not vegetable oil fat,
promotes the expansion
of the hydrogen-sulfide
generating bad bacteria,
and effects are mediated
by milk-fat promoted
taurine-conjugation bile acids.
So, to counter
any negative effects
of excess taurine consumption,
we should eat a high-fiber diet
low in saturated fat,
in other words,
a diet centered
around whole plant foods.
It reminds me of the whole,
"Vegetable nitrate strategy,"
to boost athletic performance
and slow muscle
and artery aging,
or slow aging, period,
by reducing
our resting metabolic rate.
As I discuss in my book,
How Not to Age,
the nitrate strategy
may only be safe
in the context
of a plant-based diet.
If you feed people
an amine-rich diet,
in other words
a single meal a day
with cod, salmon,
shrimp, or pollack,
along with
the nitrate equivalent
of half a cup (120 ml)
of beet juice,
you get a big jump
in the amount
of carcinogenic nitrosamines
flowing through your system.
You get a similar reaction
combining the same amount
of beet juice equivalents
with poultry, chicken,
or turkey breasts.
The nitrates turn into nitrites,
which mix
with the amines and amides
concentrated in animal foods
to form carcinogenic
nitrosamines and nitrosamides,
doubling levels within a week.
This explains
why having omnivores
drink a single bottle
of beet juice
can lead
to a significant rise
in these
carcinogenic compounds
flowing through their system
within 24 hours.
But what are the inhibitors
of this reaction
for cancer prevention?
Vitamin C, polyphenols,
and other antioxidants
found in plant foods.
So, we can add some vitamin C
to that beet juice,
and there’s less of a problem.
Just like
a healthy plant-based diet
may be necessary
to take safe advantage
of nitrate supplementation,
a healthy plant-based diet
may also be necessary
to take safe advantage
of any potential benefits
of taurine supplementation.